<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Scriptures vindication against the Scotish contradictors. By one John Stalham, and as he saith, preacher of the Gospel at Edenborough in Scotland. And the other tiled [sic], A serious review of some principles of the Quakers; wherein error is discovered, and truth defended; by P.E. and written with a pen at Edenborough, printed in the year 1655, and a written name, as if it were the printer called Peter English, but no printed name; and thus they shuffle, but laid open to their shame, and truth in this short answer is defended and cleared, and their errour is discovered, and they ensnared. Who both have manifested their contradictions both to the Scriptures, and their own writings, and so have not the people which they call Quakers. / Published by a servant of the Lord Jesus, in Yorkeshire in England, known to the world by the name of Richard Farneworth.</title>
            <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85149</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F503</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E854_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202120</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862522</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862522</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114685</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85149)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114685)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 129:E854[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Scriptures vindication against the Scotish contradictors. By one John Stalham, and as he saith, preacher of the Gospel at Edenborough in Scotland. And the other tiled [sic], A serious review of some principles of the Quakers; wherein error is discovered, and truth defended; by P.E. and written with a pen at Edenborough, printed in the year 1655, and a written name, as if it were the printer called Peter English, but no printed name; and thus they shuffle, but laid open to their shame, and truth in this short answer is defended and cleared, and their errour is discovered, and they ensnared. Who both have manifested their contradictions both to the Scriptures, and their own writings, and so have not the people which they call Quakers. / Published by a servant of the Lord Jesus, in Yorkeshire in England, known to the world by the name of Richard Farneworth.</title>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Giles Calvert at the black spread Eagle at the west end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In part a reply to "Contradictions of the Quakers (so called) to the Scriptures of God" by John Stalham; the other work has not been identified.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 2d"; "Octob. 3d".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stalham, John, d. 1681. --  Contradictions of the Quakers (so called) to the Scriptures of God --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114685:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The SCRIPTURES VINDICATION Againſt the Scotish Contradictors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By one</hi> JOHN STALHAM, <hi>and as he ſaith, Preacher of the Goſpel at</hi> Edenborough <hi>in</hi> Scotland.</p>
            <p>And the other tiled, <hi>A ſerious review of ſome Principles of the Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AKERS;</hi> wherein error is diſcovered, and truth defended; By <hi>P. E.</hi> and written with a pen at <hi>Edenborough,</hi> Printed in the year 1655, and a written name, as if it were the Printer called <hi>Peter Engliſh,</hi> but no Printed name; and thus they ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle, but laid open to their ſhame, and truth in this ſhort anſwer is defended and cleared, and their errour is diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and they enſnared.</p>
            <p>Who both have manifeſted their Contradictions both to the Scriptures, and their own writings, and ſo have not the people which they call <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>For the wiſdome of this World is fooliſhneſſe with God, and as it is written, the Lord taketh the wiſe in their own craftineſſe: And againe, the Lord knoweth the thoughts of the wiſe that they are vaine,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1</hi> Cor <hi>3.19, 20.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed by a ſervant of the Lord Jeſus, in <hi>Yorkeſhire</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> known to the world by the name of RICHARD FARNEWORTH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the black ſpread <hi>Eagle</hi> at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:114685:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114685:2"/>
            <head>To the honeſt Godly conſcientious READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EADER,</hi> If thou would ſhew thy diligence ſo far, as to take the paines to enquire and get the Books which <hi>John Stalham</hi> hath quoted in the margent of his Booke, and in reading them, and his, and alſo this, it will let thee ſee how he hath wronged them, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken here a word or two, and there a word or two, and mixed his deceite amongſt them; but however the books of themſelves are clear and clears themſelves of his ſlanders; and this for the ſimple ones ſake have I written, that they may beware of his deceits, and alſo that they may ſee and take notice how his imaginations, though the ſpirit of deceit , hath darkned his underſtanding, and miſinformed his minde, and through the working of the ſpirit of deceit is his heart given over to lye, ſlander, and falſly accuſe; and much ſtuffe there in his Epiſtle, which is made uſe of as a ſlander, but it ſtands off from us, and that, with the reſt of his lyes, ſlanders, and falſe accuſations, is back up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him returned: And where he ſaith, Light without Scripture (in his <hi>8</hi> page) is no light to them; It is but as the reſt of his ſayings, from that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful ſpirit that guides him; And if Light without Scripture or letter be no Light to them, then he knowes not the Light that was before Scripture or let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was, and ſo is ignorant of Chriſt the true Light; and it is no marvell that he ſo much oppoſeth the truth, and the work of God, that would not have God to be God, and Chriſt to be Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> without the letter of the Scripture, and if the Scriptures ſhould be loſt, he would have no God nor Chriſt, that would have none without them, to wit the Scriptures: And he ſaith, Chriſt teacheth them not to receive ſalvation, nor the word of life, without the letter of the Scripture; and becauſe one ſaid, he ſpoke the word of the Lord to them, as he ſayes, and ſpoke not Scripture, (though he ſpoke not contrary to Scripture) as in <hi>Edward Burroughs Booke</hi> to <hi>Underbarrow,</hi> yet they could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, and ſaith, without Scripture the word of the Lord could not be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, or to that effect; here he would limit the ſpirit of God: And if <hi>Samuel</hi> and the reſt of the Prophets might have ſpoken nothing to the people but what was in <hi>Moſes</hi> writings before them, they might not many times have ſpoken the word of the Lord to the people, becauſe they ſpoke that which <hi>Moſes</hi> had not written; and if Chriſt and the Apoſtles might have ſpoken nothing but what they found written in <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets writings, they might not have ſpoken much of what they did ſpeak, beſides much which is not recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, neither in writing, much that they ſpoke, as the Scriptures witneſſeth; and if <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelation:</hi> might not have ſpoken any thing but what was written before, he might not have ſpoken much of what he did; but God
<pb facs="tcp:114685:3"/>was not to be limited, neither is he now ſo to be limited as vaine men would have him; but he reveals the deep things by his ſpirit, and teaches by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſends forth his meſſengers by his ſpirit, and guides by his ſpirit into all truth, ſuch as obey his Light and follow him, which light is perfect in its leaſt meaſure, according to the manifeſtation, and manifeſts the deceits of the heart, and is the condemnation of thoſe that hate it and act contrary to it, and it the guide out of darkneſſe into the Light of life, to ſuch as follow and obey it, and the ſpirit and power of God is the ſaints ground of acting now, as it was both in the Prophets and Apoſtles, which the Scriptures declares of; and the Lord God, and his ſpirit ſent them to witnes his truth; and (not the letter) Iſaiah ſaid, The Lord God and his ſpirit ſent him, and that was the ground of his acting, <hi>Iſa. 48.16, 17.</hi> The ſpirit of Chriſt which was in the Prophets did teach them, and by it were they acted, and it did ſignifie to them, and teſtified in them before hand of the ſufferings of Chriſt and the glory that ſhould follow <hi>1 Pet. 10, 11.</hi> and Chriſt gave command to his Diſciples before he aſcended to wait at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> till they received power from on high, and then ſhould they witneſſe him to the ends of the earth; and they had the letter before, but the ſpirit was more ſure, and the perfect rule in the Church, <hi>Acts 1. John 16 13. Rom. 8.14.</hi> And the holy Ghoſt ſent forth workmen, ſo did not the letter, <hi>Acts 13.</hi> And the holy Ghoſt made ever ſeers in the Church of Chriſt, ſo did not the letter; though the letter declare of it, <hi>Acts 20.28.</hi> and they that preached the Goſpel, preached it with the holy Ghoſt, ſent down from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>1 Pet. 1.14.</hi> and Chriſt Jeſus was both the Saints ground of acting, and the foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles, and not the letter, as they in <hi>Scotland</hi> affirme; yet the letter declares of it, and contradicts their affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, witneſſed in <hi>Eph. 2.18, 19, 20. &amp;c.</hi> and Chriſt is the true light, and lightneth every one that comes into the world, and it not natural, as they in <hi>Scotland</hi> affirme; But the ſpirituall ſaving light to all that obey him, as the Scriptures witnes, contrary to their affirmitive, witneſſed in <hi>Joh. 1.9. Joh. 8.12. Heb. 5.8, 9.</hi> and the Scriptures in the letter onely are not the true ground of the believers faith, as they in <hi>Scotland</hi> affirme; but Chriſt is the true groud of faith, as the Scriptures ſay, contrary to their affirmative, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed in <hi>Heb. 12.2.</hi> and they have faith in God, and are upheld by his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that abide in the true faith; and the Spirit is not in the letter, nor given by it, as the <hi>Scots</hi> affirme, but the letter declares of the ſpirit, and it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the letter was, and given by the Lord, it is his gift, and not the gift of the letter, yet the letter declares of it, but God is the giver, contrary to their affirmation, witneſſed in <hi>John 14.16, 17. John 14.26. John 16.13. Acts 2. Gal. 4.6. 1 John 3.24.</hi> There it no ſpirit and life in outward bread and wine, neither is Chriſt ſpiritually in it at the inſtitution, as the Papiſts and <hi>Scots</hi> affirme; Therefore they contradicts the Scriptures, and the late Act of Abjuration, that ſo affirme; For Chriſt it the bread of life, <hi>John 6.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch as eate that bread live in him, and he in them, <hi>Ver. 57, 58.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114685:3"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION OF THE SCRIPTURES, In Anſwer to the Scottiſh Contradictors.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Received a Printed Paper that came out of <hi>Scotland</hi> into <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Yorkeſhire</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> publiſhed by one <hi>John Stalham</hi> (and as he calls himſelfe) Preacher of the Goſpel at <hi>Edenborough</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Scotland;</hi> but he hath manifeſted himſelfe, and his ſubtile and ſerpentine ſpirit, by his lies and ſlanders, for all his gloſſes and covers, to be a Miniſter of deceit, and ſo of Antichriſt, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after will more appear, who falſly accuſes the people of the Lord, and ſhewes forth a bitter ſpirit of envy againſt them and the truth, which doth manifeſt his deceit, and though he be painted and deckt with his notions, implications, and contra di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions, and gilded, coloured, and borrowed, and form'd up imagined expreſſions; yet with the Light, which is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reaſon (as he calls it) but the true Light which diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth errour and deceit, and leads out of darkneſſe into the light of life, <hi>John</hi> 8.12. ſuch as obey it: with the Light (<hi>John.</hi> 1.9.) is he ſeen and known to be one that hates it, and alſo bears record of himſelf againſt Chriſt, and his Apoſtles; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114685:4"/>he muſt needs be an antichriſtian and a deceiver, and ſo to be denyed and holden accurſed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9. For he calls the true Light the light of nature, and the common light of reaſon, but cannot prove what he hath therein ſaid; Therefore he is a lyar, a falſe accuſer; and lyars and falſe accuſers are antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, ſo is he; Therefore let him be an <hi>Anathema Maranatha,</hi> and all ſuch as he is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To that which thou calls touching the Scriptures themſelves.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Stalham,</hi> Thou calls thy Pamphlet (or Book of lyes) The <hi>Quakers</hi> Contradictions; to the Scriptures, and to that which thou begins with, and calls it, Touching the Scriptures themſelves. Firſt thou ſayes, They ſay the Scriptures are not the word of truth: I anſwer, That the Scriptures are words that proceeded from the ſpirit of truth, we doe not deny but own, and ſo they are words of truth; and therefore thy ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is falſe, and in that thou art charged to be a lyar, and falſe accuſer of the truth; but that the Scriptures are the Word, God, and eternal Life, as thou wouldſt have them, thou canſt not prove, nor all the Magicians to help thee; and that thou wouldſt have them to be, and thou art ſeen to be a lyar of them and the truth; and ſuch as witnes to the word, and Gods pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, they witneſse againſt thee. And where thou Queries and ſayes, How can the Scriptures be Gods witneſse if not true? I anſwer, That the ſpirit of truth in the Prophets were Gods witneſse, and teſtified before-hand of the ſufferings of Chriſt, and declared of in the Scriptures by words that proceeded from that ſpirit of Chriſt, that in them did ſignifie thoſe things, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. And the ſpirit of Chriſt, in the Apoſtles of Chriſt <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. did carry them forth after they had received power from on high to witnes him forth, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. But the ſpirit is not in the letter, as thou in thy 22 page hath ſaid, neither is the ſpirit gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the letter, but by God and Chriſt, of whom the letter doth declare, being words of truth that proceeded from the ſpirit of truth, <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 1 <hi>John</hi> 13. The letter proceeded from the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but the ſpirit did not proceed from the letter; and therein thou haſt erred, not knowing the ſpirit nor power of God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared of in the Scriptures. Thou ſaith, Another ſaith the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114685:4"/>Scripture is not a ſtanding rule, to you who cannot believe; contrary to <hi>Luke</hi> 16.29. They have <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets for a ſtanding rule, thou ſayes: Here let all the honeſt hearted judge of thy deceite, who hath perverted that Scripture for thy own ends, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.29. from it raiſing a falſe doctrine; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, You have <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets for a ſtanding rule, when the ver: ſaith not ſo; here I charge thee in the preſence of the Lord to be a lyar of the Scriptures, and ſo contradicts them, for if <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets had been left (to all and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver) for a ſtanding rule, as thou aſſerts, then Chriſt and the Apoſtles might not have been after <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets for following examples, or rules; and therein thou brings the old Covenant to contradict the new, and croſſeth that Scripture, where it ſaith, Be ye followers of God as dear children, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.1. And they that follow him in the Goſpel, are led by his Spirit, and that is not the letter, though the letter declare of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For God is that ſpirit, as ſaith the Scripture, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17. But we follow God, who are guided by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as ſuch did; and that is our guide and rule, to wit, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of truth, as Chriſt hath (ſince he promiſed it) appointed it, to be the rule and guide into all truth, <hi>John</hi> 16.13. But thou that would have the letter to be the rule, and <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets onely; then thou wouldſt not have Chriſt and the Apoſtles followed after; and ſo contradicts the Scripture alſo, which was ſpoken after <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, after the Law, under the Goſpel, by a miniſter of the ſame, who in his godly exhortation ſaid, Be ye followers of me, even as I am of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. And that was not <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, but Chriſt and his Apoſtles there ſpoken of: Seeing then we are not under the Law, but under Grace, the ſpirit of Chriſt is our rule and guide; and even unto this day when <hi>Moſes</hi> is read, the vaile is upon their heart, as ſaith the Scripture, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.15. But thou art reading and pleading for <hi>Moſes</hi> to be a ſtanding rule, and ſo ſets up the Law in ſtead of the Goſpel, therefore the vaile is upon thy heart; but we witneſse the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that exceeds, for if the miniſtration of condemnation were glorious, much more the miniſtration of glory exceeds, but thou art ignorant of that; and where thou haſt pleaded for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114685:5"/>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets to be a ſtanding rule, ſaying, they have <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, let them heart them, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.31. Here thou ſayes the Scriptures are aſſerted by our Lord to be a more ſtanding rule then Viſions and Revelations; thou haſt here raiſed a falſ aſſertion, of the Lord, ſaying, he aſſerts it, and the aſſertion is thine, and not the Lords, therefore thou art a lyar and falſe accuſer of the Lord; for he ſaith in <hi>Matthew</hi> 11.27. that no man knoweth the Son but the Father, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knoweth any man the Father ſave the Sonne, and he to whomſoever the Son (not the Scripture, but the Son) will reveal him; here Revelation is the ſurer rule of knowing God, witneſſed alſo <hi>Luke</hi> 10.22. And viſions are a way of God making known himſelfe by, as was witneſſed after <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, and thou contradicts the Scriptures, for the Lord ſpoke to <hi>Ananias</hi> his meſſenger in a viſion, and gave him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to go with his meſſage, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.10, 11. and that was a more ſure knowlege to him then the words of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, and a rule that ſtood firmer to him then words of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men: And <hi>Paul,</hi> he ſaw in a viſion the man named <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanias</hi> come unto him, ver: 12. and that was more certaine then the words of others, as <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets: And <hi>Peter</hi> ſaw in a viſion thing; cleared to him, which was not clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the writings of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.15, 16, 17. and while <hi>Peter</hi> thought on the viſion, the ſpirit ſpoke unto him, and gave him commiſſion to go to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, ver: 19, 20, &amp;c. but ſo did not the Scriptures, then the Scriptures are not a more ſure or ſtanding rule, then viſions and revelations by the ſpirit of truth are, as thou ſayes, therefore thou art a lyar and falſe accuſer therein; for <hi>Paul</hi> knew Chriſt by revelation, and received the Goſpel by revelation, as he hath certified to the brethren, <hi>Ga.</hi> 1.11, 12. and when Chriſt was revealed within him, he went to preach him, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15, 16. and that was a ſure rule unto him, and more ſure then the Scriptures, for he knew much of the writings of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Prophets, and letter of the Scriptures, whileſt he were a perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor, but then he knew not Chriſt revealed in him, which after he did, and went up to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> fourteen years after by reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. and not by the Scriptures; therefore the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114685:5"/>are not ſo ſure a rule as viſions and revelations by the ſpirit of truth are; and the Apoſtle knew how ſure revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by the ſpirit of truth were, ſo he exhorted others to wait for the grace that was to be brought to them at the revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13. and the deep things of God are revealed (not by the letter, but) by the ſpirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. Therefore Revelations by the ſpirit of truth are more ſure then the Letter; for the righteouſneſſe of God is revealed from faith unto faith, as faith the Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. through the Goſpel and power of God unto ſalvation, ver. 16, 17.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayes that one ſaith, the Scriptures are other mens words, contrary to 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. the Scripture is given by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration; And then by a peece of logick thou wouldſt raiſe a falſ accuſation againſt <hi>Francis Howgill,</hi> and makes a falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion to wreſt the Scriptures to ſerve thy own turne, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not; as for <hi>Francis Howgill</hi> ſaying the Scriptures are other mens words; thou ſets down truth defended, page 6. Let the wiſe hearted read that Book, and it clears him from thy ſlander which by thy logick thou wouldſt caſt upon him, becauſe he ſayes the Scriptures are other mens words, that ſpoke them free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (and not for ſet wages, or hundreds a year, &amp;c.) And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I anſwer, Holy men of God ſpoke as they were moved, ſo ſaith the Scripture, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. and it doth not contradict the 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. where it ſayes, the Scriptures are given by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of God, then the Scripture was inſpired, and that was by the ſpirit, and ſpirituall men ſpoke forth thoſe words; Therefore they were words ſpoken by the men of God, and ſo words from the ſpirit of truth, ſpoken by the holy men of God, (other men) that were holy and ſpoke freely, and not by you that are ſinfull and pleads for it, and Preaches for hire the words of others, as the falſe Prophets did; therefore the Lord is againſt you hireling Prieſts in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch in your nature ſpoken of in Scripture: Read thoſe Scriptures to be witneſſe againſt all thoſe Scottiſh Prieſts, that Preach for hire, and ſeeks for the fleece &amp;c. and makes a prey upon the people, and ſeeks for their gaine from their quarter, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 5.30, 31. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. <hi>Micah</hi> 3.11. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.10, 11.2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>Jude</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:114685:6"/>
That the Scriptures are the words of other men, and not yours: Read the words of the Preacher, the ſonne of <hi>David,</hi> King in Iſrael, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1. Read the words alſo of King <hi>Lemuel</hi> and he was a man; read the Prophecy that his mother taught him and ſhe was a woman, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31. The ſong of ſongs which is <hi>Solomens,</hi> and he was a man, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1. There is the words of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the ſon of <hi>Hilkiah, Jer.</hi> 1.1. To whom the word of the Lord came in the days of <hi>Joſiah</hi> King of Judah in the 18 year of his Reigne; but a Printed Bible did not come unto him; neither did he nor any Prophet or Apoſtle that thou canſt prove ever ſtand with a Printed Bible in his hand and ſay, hear the word of the Lord: Then the word of the Lord was declared and ſpoken without Printed Bibles, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Printing was invented; But if Printing had not been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, what would you have Preached by that knows not the word of life, which was before writing or Printing was?</p>
               <p>And where thou ſayes (they ſay) you have nothing to try mens Doctrine and ſpirit by, but the letter, and that your tryer is a chapter or a verſe of the Scriptures; no more you Scotiſh Preiſts have: for thou ſayes the letter is ſpirit, or the ſpirit is in the letter, and given by it; By this thou haſt manifeſted thy Scottiſh tryer, and as for that ſaying, to the Law, and to the Teſtimony, if they ſpeak not according to it, it is becauſe there is no light in them; but we ſpeak according to it, and therefore there is Light in us; For God who commanded the Light to ſhine out of darkneſſe, hath ſhined in our hearts, &amp;c. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6, 7. And where thou accuſeſt <hi>James Nayler</hi> for ſaying, the Law of the new Covenant is written in the heart, it is but to manifeſt thy ignorance of it, and that thou art offended at <hi>James</hi> for witneſſing what the Scriptures do witnes, and that the Law of the new Covenant is written in the heart, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.31, <hi>&amp;c. Heb.</hi> 8 10, 11. And where thou ſayes for any to call the written word, which is the letter of the Scripture, carnall is blaſphemy; Here againe thou haſt ſhewed that thou regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not what thou ſayes, and art ignorant of what the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelfe faith concerning the ſame, which ſpeaketh of a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall commandement; but that is all one with thy other, that ſayes the ſpirit is in the letter, and the letter is the word, but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114685:6"/>cannot with all that thou haſt ſcraped together prove that it is the word which is eternal life; and ſo the word that was in the beginning with God, and was God, <hi>John</hi> 1.1.</p>
               <p>Thou accuſeſt them for ſaying the ſaints ground of acting is not the outward Letter, but the Spirit which gave forth the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and ſaith, here they ſet the word at diſtance from the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſets figurative gloſſes upon the Scriptures; Here thou art blinded and knows not the Saints ground, and art accuſing them falſly that witneſse to it; and ſayes, they ſet the word at diſtance from the ſpirit: The word and ſpirit cannot be ſet at (difference nor) diſtance except God could be devided, and that cannot be, for God is the word, <hi>John</hi> 1.1. and God is that ſpirit, 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 3.17. Therefore the word and the ſpirit are inſeperable, but the Letter is not God, nor the letter is not the ſpirit; therefore not that word which liveth and abideth for ever, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. by which word the World was framed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.3. and made, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. In which word is the life and the Light of men, which the Letter doth declare of, but is not the life and Light of men, neither were all things made by the letter that were made, but by the word they were, <hi>John</hi> 1.1, 2, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is plain Scripture without figurative gloſſe; the gloſſes are thy own, that with thy logick and magick art would make the Scriptures God and Chriſt, but cannot; and would make them the ground of the Saints actings, when they are not, but the Lord God and his ſpirit is; for the Lord God and his ſpirit ſent me ſaith the ſervant of the Lord, <hi>Iſa</hi> 48. and the Lord teacheth his that he ſo ſends to profit, <hi>v.</hi> 16, 17. and the manifeſtation of the ſpirit is given to profit withall, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. and ſaith God, <hi>I will poure out of my ſpirit and your ſons and daughters ſhall propheſie,</hi> and ſuch may ſpeak of the things of God: Thy meanings I deny, and the fancy is thy own, and the ſure word of Propheſie we witneſse to, and do not to it ſay no; therefore in that thou haſt further uttered thy lyes, and manifeſted thy deceitfull ſpirit; as in page 7. Thou ſayes, they ſay there is no Scripture for the Trinity, contrary to <hi>John</hi> 5.7. which expreſly ſaith, <hi>There are three that beare witneſſe in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the Father the Word and the Spirit, and theſe three are all one,</hi> here is Trinity thou ſayes; here thou haſt perverted the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114685:7"/>ſaying here is Trinity, when it expreſſeth no ſuch word in that nor any other Scripture as Trinity, but the Father Son and Spirit which are one, that we witneſſe; and as Chriſt hath ſaid, At that day ye ſhall know that I am in my Father, and you in me, and I in you, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.20. The Father Son and holy Ghoſt are one, but it doth not ſpeak of diſtinct perſons three, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou art yet to prove a Trinity: The Holy Ghoſt is no perſon, but dwelleth in perſons or bodies of Saints, and he that abideth in the doctrine of Chriſt hath both the Father and the Son, as ſaith the Scripture in the 2 Epiſtle of <hi>John</hi> 9—</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Light, and Chriſt the way to the Father.</head>
               <p>That Chriſt is the way to the Father is ſet down in <hi>Edward Burroughs</hi> Book to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderbarrow,</hi> p. 4. and that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures witneſs and do not contradict, <hi>John</hi> 14.6. but thou haſt wreſted <hi>Edward Burroughs</hi> words, and therefore thou art a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; there is not ſuch a word as [purchaſed] in that page, and there lyeth the weight of thy matter; but that Chriſt is the true Light that enlightneth every man that cometh into the World, the Scriptures witneſſe, <hi>John</hi> 1.9. Therefore if thou ſay the contray, the Scriptures thou therein contradictteſt, (and not he) take notice of that; and withall that Chriſt is the Light of the World, and a ſaving Light to all that obey him as ſaith the Scriptures; and ſuch as follow him the true Light are by him led out of darkneſſe into the light of life, as he hath ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 8.12. <hi>Heb</hi> 5.8, 9 and that word, magnifie the Light thou puts in; but if we do and as <hi>Mary</hi> did, we magnifie the Lord (1 <hi>John</hi> 1.5.) and art thou offended at that? there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou contradicts the Scripture; where it ſaith, <hi>My ſoule doth magnifie the Lord,</hi> Luke 1.26. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.29, 30, 31, 32. and thou alſo contradicts thy ſelfe, and lyes againſt Chriſt the true Light, calling him naturall, and common, and lyes of ſuch as witneſſe Chriſt, and the Light of his ſpirit and according to the declaration of the Scriptures: And where thou art offended at <hi>George Fox</hi> for ſaying the light of Chriſt is life, it is but to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt thy envy againſt the truth, and thy contradictions to the Scriptures, for the Scripture ſaith, Chriſt is the Light, <hi>John</hi> 1.9. and he is life even the way the truth and the life, <hi>John.</hi> 14. and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114685:7"/>ſuch as follow him the true Light are led out of darkneſſe (er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and deceit) into the Light of Life, <hi>John</hi> 8.12. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine thou accuſeſt <hi>George Fox</hi> for ſaying the light is the word, but it is but to manifeſt thy further contradictions to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for the Scripture ſayes God is the Light, <hi>John</hi> 1.5. and God is the Word, <hi>John</hi> 1.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore in that thou haſt manifeſted thy ignorance of the Scriptures, and knows not the Light and the word; for as God is the Light and the Word ſo alſo is Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 8.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.13. and the Father and Son are one, and ſuch as abide in the doctrine of Chriſt have the Light and the Word of God abiding in them, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.12, 13, 14. and they may ſpeak from it that have fellowſhip with it: And thou ſayes, they would ſend you to read the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the creatures, quoting the Book of parables; That Book ſhal witneſſe for the truth againſt thee and thy generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and alſo let the wiſe hearted take notice that he that is in Chriſt is a new creature, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16, 17. and that they are Epiſtles written in one anothers hearts, ſeen and read in one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother that are ſuch creatures, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. And there again thou haſt ſhewed thy ignorance of thoſe Epiſtles, and lyed of the truth with thy deceitfull ſpirit, by twiſting and winding about; but thou may well lye of us that lyes of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> and wreſts not our words onely but his alſo; for where thou ſpeaks his words, where he ſayes, <hi>It pleaſed God by the fooliſhneſſe of Preaching</hi> (and as thou ſayes a Text a Doctrine a Reaſon an Uſe out of the Word) <hi>to ſave them that beleive;</hi> when there is not any ſuch words of his there as Text Doctrine Reaſon Uſe to ſave them that beleive; and here thou haſt lyed of him, and thou wouldſt make the Letter a Saviour, for thou calls that the Word; and ſo thou wouldſt have a ſalvation without Chriſt (except thou make the letter of the Scripture Chriſt) and there againe thou haſt contradicted the Scripture, which calls Chriſt the alone Saviour, or perfect Saviour, being able to ſave all that come unto God by him, (not by the Scripture) but by Chriſt the alone and perfect Saviour of ſuch, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.11, 12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. which the Scripture declareth of; and he that hath the Son hath life, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.12. (if he have not the letter) but he that hath not the Son hath not life (though he may have
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114685:8"/>all the Letter:) And where thou ſayes that <hi>Edward Burrough</hi> calls the common light the corner ſtone, &amp;c. Thou lyes of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Burrough,</hi> and his Book to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderbarrow,</hi> p. 7. for there is not ſuch a word as a common Light there, ſtop thy mouth lyar, for thou art taken with the lye in thy mouth, and lyars are for the Lake, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8 But the Scripture ſaith, Chriſt is the Light, and Chriſt is the chief corner ſtone, <hi>Act</hi> 4.11. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6, 7. and ſo ſaith <hi>Edward Burrough;</hi> therefore he agrees with the Scripture, and his ſaying (as thou ſayes) is not contrary to <hi>Eph.</hi> 2 20. but agree therewith; there againe thou art taken with another lye in thy mouth, lyar be aſhamed and bluſh: And where thou wouldſt ſlander <hi>Richard Farneworth</hi> for ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Light is pure ſtanding out of corruption; thy ſlander hath no weight nor doth not harm, for God is Light, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.5. and he is pure, and diſcovers corruptions, and hath no uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with them; therefore his Light is pure and ſtands out of them, and what communion hath Light with darkneſſe, as ſaith the Scripture, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14. And thou brings that Scripture and ſayes, if you beleivers ſay you have no ſin, you deceive your ſelves and the truth is not in you, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8. But I ſay, and ſo doth the Scripture, that he that abideth in Chriſt ſinneth not, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.6. But you Scotchmen abide not in Chriſt (that thou calls beleivers) who plead for the Devil, and therefore are ſinners; and ſuch as commit ſin, are of the Devil, take notice of that, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.6, 7, 8, 9, 10. but thou commits ſin and ſo art a ſervant of the Devil; for thou goes on with thy lies and ſayes, <hi>James Nayler</hi> ſaith that the common Light of every man (which thou calls naturall Light) being followed and obeyed will lead out of the fall; I charge thee here in the preſence of the Lord to be a lyar of <hi>James Nayler</hi> and his Book; for the words in it are not as thou ſayes, thou lyar and falſe accuſer be aſhamed of thy lyes; but <hi>James Nayler</hi> witneſseth with Chriſt who is the true Light, and ſuch as obey the Light and follow Chriſt they are led thereby out of the fall and are ſaved by him and that is not contrary to Scripture but witneſsed with it, which thou contradicts, and ſo ſins againſt Scripture and againſt Chriſt that calls him a naturall Light: and to manifeſt thy blindneſſe and ignorance of the Scriptures, thou ſayes, Where is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114685:8"/>Promiſe in Scripture, of ſpirituall ſaving Light, to lead man out of the fall and out of his naturall eſtate? but a threatning thou ſayes there is, &amp;c. I anſwer, If there were no Promiſe of ſpirituall ſaving Light to lead out of the fall, man might conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in it, and under the curſe; but there is Promiſes of ſaving Light and ſaving grace anexed to it, and ſuch as follow and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the ſame are ſaved by it, and led out of the fall; for by grace are we ſaved through faith, and not of our ſelves, it is the gift of God, as ſaith the Scripture, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. <hi>Not of works leaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man ſhould boaſt,</hi> Eph. 2.8, 9. That there is promiſes of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Light in Scripture; as God hath ſaid, <hi>I will give thee for a Covenant of the people, for a Light to the Gentiles,</hi> and this Light hath grace anexed, that is a covenanting Light, <hi>and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to the ends of the earth, the Light of the Gentiles, and the glory of the people Iſrael,</hi> Iſa. 42.6, 7. Iſa. 49.6. Iſa. 60.19, 20. Luke 2.22, 23. Eph. 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Law.</head>
               <p>To that touching the Law and firſt Covenant of works, that the Moſaicall and Leviticall Law was under that Covenant of works, and all thy twiſting and wreſting cannot diſprove it; and for thy ſaying <hi>Adam</hi> was under a Covenant of works (and the ſame) thou canſt not prove it, nor <hi>Peter Engliſh</hi> to help thee, but manifeſts your confuſion therein; for <hi>Peter Engliſh</hi> in his ſerious reveiw, ſaith that God made <hi>Adam</hi> upright, p. 7. and in a ſtate of perfection; for he ſaith, <hi>Adam</hi> was made in a ſtate of perfection without ſin; and yet to contradict himſelfe, and ſhew his confuſion, in p. 10 he ſaith, that through cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe the root of all evill, a breach of the 10 commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, he fell (or brake) and tranſgreſſing dyed; ſee here how <hi>Peter Engliſh</hi> hath befooled himſelfe; firſt ſaith he, man was perfect and without ſin; then ſaith he, he was coveteous and in the root of all evill, what contradictions is here to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to the Scripture, that ſaith, before he ſo fell he knew no evill: and the ſaid <hi>Peter Engliſh</hi> (a Scotchman) ſaith fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to confute himſelfe and the reſt with him, that it cannot be ſaid that <hi>Adam</hi> in a ſtate of innocency was under a covenant of works, p. 9. for where there is no Law there is no tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114685:9"/>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.15. and the Law is not for the righteous but for the rebellions, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. and ſo he ſaith in a ſence <hi>Nayler</hi> ſpoke true; but <hi>Peter Engliſh</hi> going about to accuſe <hi>Nayler,</hi> and after when he hath cleared him, he confutes himſelfe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Adam</hi> was not under a covenant of works, as under a Law, and yet ſaith through a breach of the 10 commandement he broke the covenant, and tranſgreſſing of which he died: here he hath comed poorly off, and lyed of himſelf, and of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and of <hi>Adam</hi> alſo; for he ſaid, where no Law was there was no traſgreſſion: but <hi>Adam</hi> had not the Law in which the 10 commandments were given, therefore he did not tranſgreſs the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and dye for that; for it were written (the Law with the 10 commandements) ſeveral hundred years after <hi>Adam,</hi> and not given to him in the Paradice, therefore he was not under that Law and Covenant of works; Lyars ſtop your mouths.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Sinne.</head>
               <p>That all the children of Light are called to judg them Prieſts, and ſuch as you that ſay the children of God are found groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning under the burden of ſinne all their life time, thoſe are the words, though thou wreſt them, (that is warranted and not ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roganted) for groaning under ſinne whileſt it is working out, that may be, but to ſay that the children of God they groane under it all their life time, it contradicts the Scriptures, and the arrogant aſſertion is thy own, contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. for thou ſayes <hi>Paul</hi> all along in <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. from v. 14. ſpeaks in the name of the regenerate to the end of the chapter, and groans and ſighs it out, <hi>Oh wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from this body of death?</hi> here though <hi>Paul</hi> did cry out of the body of death, he did not always groan and ſigh as diſſemblers [and Scots] doe, neither did he doe it in the name of all the regenerate, as thou ſayes, but ſpoke his owne condition there: therefore thou haſt lyed groſly therein, and ſo art an impudent lyar: And <hi>Paul</hi> did not alwayes groan un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that body of ſin and Law in his members, but witneſsed a redemption from it, for which he thanked God that made him more then a conqueror, and others as well as he, and ſuch did not commit ſin, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.9. and then not alwayes groaning
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114685:9"/>under, that were delivered from it, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.1, 5, 6— And to manifeſt thy confuſion thou ſayes, the children of God from their new birth puts of the body of ſin, as to guilt and reigning power, and yet ſin eaſily beſets them and preſſeth down by the remnants of filth (thou ſayes) and that is thy condition; where it ſo eaſily beſets and preſſeth down it reigns, but it eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets and preſſeth thee and you Scotchmen, down that are in the filth of it; and therefore you let it reigne in your mortall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. and the new birth you are ignorant of, and the hope that purifieth, even as he is pure, as ſuch wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed that witneſsed and witneſſe that birth, and are Sons, 1 <hi>John.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3—</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Juſtification, and the end of the Righteous and wicked, or unrighteous.</head>
               <p>They deny that God Juſtifieth a beleiving ſinner, (thou ſayes.) I anſwer, That ſuch as are born of God doe truly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive, and faith in God purifieth their hearts and giveth them victory over the World, and ſo frees them from ſin 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. And ſuch beleivers are Juſtified from ſin and ungodlineſſe, and not in ſin and ungodlineſs; for by Chriſt ſuch as are ſo born and beleive, are Juſtified from all ſins, and ſuch like things, from which they could not be Juſtified by the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and ſo Chriſt is their Juſtification, who are Sanctified and from ſin by him redeemed; which ſin thou art pleading for, and ſo art an unbeleiver, and not redeemed, that ſayes, It cannot be routed out till body and ſoule part, and faith, then is ſin pluckt up by the roots; as the root of a wilde Figtree rooted in the joynts of a ſtone wall, is rooted our when the wall is taken down; but hath no proof for thy ſaying but thy pollicy and that is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Scripture; for it is ſaid, <hi>Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright, for the end of that man is peace,</hi> Pſal. 37.37. <hi>But the wicked ſhall be cut off, and the tranſgreſſors ſhall be deſtroyed together at their end,</hi> Pſal. 37.38. And you that plead for ſin till your latter end, continueth in wickedneſſe, and ſo are unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated, and the end of the wicked ſhall be cut off; you that continue in ſin to your end, are wicked tranſgreſſors, and ſuch
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114685:10"/>ſhall be cut off &amp; deſtroyed together; as their works are, ſo will their end be: But ſuch as are ſinners and tranſgreſſors to their end their deeds are evill ſo will their end be, and the wicked and ſuch like ſhall be turned into hell, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.17. and the unclean and unrighteous ſhall hot inherit the Kingdome of Heaven, ye unrighteous Scots look to it and read 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6 9.10 <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27—</p>
               <p>And for that ſaying of the Prieſts of <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> that ſaid <hi>Peter</hi> when he denyed Chriſt was in a ſtate of Juſtification and that a man denying Chriſt is in a ſtate of Juſtification: both thy blindneſſe and theirs is there ſeen, and that Scripture which thou brings to prove <hi>Peters</hi> being in a ſtate of Juſtification when he denied Chriſt is <hi>Luke</hi> 22.33. which ſpeaks no ſuch thing, but of the Deſcipies enquirery among themſelves who it ſhould be that ſhould betray Chriſt: ſee how blinde thou art, was <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> in a ſtate of Juſtification when he denied Chriſt and betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him no more then <hi>Peter</hi> was when Chriſt called him Satan; but after <hi>Peter</hi> had repented of his deniall of Chriſt and wept bitterly, upon his return, and after he were united to the Faith, then Chriſt prayed for him: And where <hi>James Nayler</hi> in the diſcovery of the man of ſin, page 29 where he askes the Prieſts of <hi>New-Caſtle;</hi> if pleading for ſin be a diſcovering of the man of ſinne to ſtrengthen the Devils Kingdome, and plead for an upholding of ſinne, and ſeeking to make a cover for thy ſins and theirs; Thou wieſts <hi>James</hi> words in thy 12 page and art ignorant alſo of that which diſcovers the man of ſinne, that art making covers for him, and by thy pollicy thou goeſt about to make Chriſt a ſinner, but in that thy folly is ſeene, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to the Scripture, that ſaith, <hi>He was make unto us;</hi> (ſin excepted) and ſuch as are in him, are redeemed out of ſin, and abiding in him, they ſinne not, whoſoever ſinneth hath not ſeene him, neither knowne him, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.4.5.6. and ſin cannot be reconciled to God, nor any ſuch imperfect thing, and that doth not contradict the Scripture, <hi>Revel:</hi> 21.27. And as for our meaning thou ſpeakes of, thou art without our minde, and ſo knoweſt not our meaning, by thy Imagining; therein thou ſhewes a ſpirit of errour; And where thou ſayeſt, they ſay, he that beleiveth is borne of God without Scripture, and yet wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114685:10"/>in Scripture is contrary to <hi>James.</hi> 1.17. where it ſaith, <hi>Of his owne will begot he us by the word of Truth;</hi> and to <hi>Peter,</hi> where it ſayes, <hi>Being borne againe by the word of God, which li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth and abideth for ever,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.22, 23. But if thou was not blinde, thou would ſee that thou Contradicts the Scripture, and not them; that attributes the worke of regeneration and the new birth to the Letter, which thou cals the word, and ſo there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in denyes God; who begets by his owne will, by that word which liveth and abideth for ever; which was in the beginning with God, and was God; And where thou ſayes they ſay, ſin dwelleth not in act where Chriſt reigneth; that is true; for where Chriſt raignes, the body is dead to the acts of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, becauſe of ſin being deſtroyed, and the Spirit is Life becauſe of righteouſneſſe, Living and ruling; and here thou art contradicting the Scriptures, and oppoſing the worke of Chriſt, which is to take away ſin, and ſuch as abides in him ſinnes not, then ſin acts not, he that acts ſin commits ſin, and there Chriſt raignes not but Antichriſt, under whoſe Dominion thou art, that pleads for him and his worke; but hee that is begotten of God keepeth himſelfe, and that wicked one toucheth him not; and hee that acteth and doth righteouſneſſe is of God, but hee that acteth and doth unrighteouſneſſe is not of God, as ſaith the Scripture; And where thou ſayes they ſay perfection of holineſſe is not reſerved till after death, nothing is added after death; and ſets downe <hi>James Naylers</hi> booke, called, <hi>The Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the man of ſinne, Pag:</hi> 28. Let all that reads that booke ſee if there be ſuch words ſo expreſſed by <hi>James</hi> in that Page, and if not, as they are not ſo ſet downe by him, then let them take notice of thy deceitfull ſpirit; And as thou haſt lyed of <hi>James,</hi> who witneſseth purity as the Saints did; ſo alſo haſt thou lyed of the Apoſtle, and thoſe ſpoken of in <hi>Hebr:</hi> 12. and contradicted his words, where thou ſets downe <hi>Hebr:</hi> 12.23. ſaying from that, in contradiction to <hi>James,</hi> that he contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts that Scripture, when hee witneſseth with it, but thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts it that ſayes, that the Spirits, that is, ſoules ſeperated (as thou ſayes) from the bodyes of Juſt men made perfect, in holineſſe: which is at death, or at an Inſtant when the Spirit is ſeperated from the Body; ſin is as the wild figtree thou ſayes,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114685:11"/>rooted in the Joints of a Stonewall, and when the wall is taken downe, the ſtones caſt aſunder, body and ſoule ſeperated, then is ſin (thou ſayes) pluckt up by the rootes, as the roots of a figtree, and not before; Thou ſubtile Serpent, and Scotch Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titian, how haſt thou wreſted the Scripture? The Apoſtle ſaith that the word of the Lord is quicke and powerfull, (ſo is not the Letter of the Scripture,) to devide aſunder ſoule and ſpirit, Joints and Marrow, and is A deſcerner of the thoughts and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the heart; <hi>Heb:</hi> 4.12. Here ſoule and ſpirit is devided by the Living word, and the Ground of ſin ſhaken at the roots and rooted out of ſuch, before their ſoules and bodyes part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder; for thoſe that thou ſpeakes of in <hi>Heb:</hi> 12.22. did not ſay it ſhould be at an Inſtant of death, when their bodyes and ſoule parted, that they ſhould be perfected; but they witneſſed that then they was come to Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> and to the Citie of the Living God, to the Innumerable company of Angells, and to the ſpirits of Juſt men made perfect; and in the preſent Tenſe they there ſpoke, and not in the future; and doth it ſay, they was then parting body and ſoule aſunder, or that ſin was roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in them, as the wild figtree is rooted in the Joints of a ſtone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall, and did they ſay, when the wall is taken downe, the ſtones caſt aſunder, body and ſoule parted, then ſhould ſin be rooted out, and not before; or then they was in that ſtate of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they ſpoke of; but by this thou haſt manifeſted thy Scottiſh pollicy, and Antichriſtian deceitfull Spirit, and to be one that would uphold the Kingdome of the Devill in people, and ſo art an enemie to Chriſt, and his worke, which is to take away ſin here; and to ſanctifie by his Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 6.11. 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 3, 4, 5. and ſo art againſt purity and holineſſe here; and therefore againſt the Scripture, which ſaith, <hi>As hee that hath called you is holy, ſo be yee holy in all manner of converſation;</hi> But thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes the holy call alſo, as well as the holy converſation, that pleads for ſin, to act, and preſſe downe, and make you all your Lift time to ſigh it our, and under it groane, but that is one of your Scottiſh tricks of deceipt, take notice of that.</p>
               <p>And where thou haſt ſhewed forth another piece of thy pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy and ſerpentine ſubtilty, from the words as thou ſayes, in the ſhort Anſwer, <hi>Pag:</hi> 1. They are not ſo ſet downe there, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114685:11"/>therefore thy pollicy hath manifeſted ſubtilty, and thy particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar lyes; But all thy pleading is againſt purity, yet Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God,</hi> Math: 5.8. then there was and are pure in heart, as Chriſt ſaid, and they are bleſſed, but thou ſees it not, that art of a corrupt heart, and pleading againſt Chriſt and his doctrine, and ſo accurſed; and thy witchcraft and deceipt; that Loves not purity in heart, nor the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and what hee hath therein ſaid: And where thou ſayes thou art ſure that the leaſt degree of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity makes a ſoule ſenſible of continuall Impurities mixed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, That is thy owne condition, confirmed by thy aſſurance, and ſo thou Judges others by thy Continuall Impurities, and therefore thy Judgement muſt needs be falſe, and not true, and that is thy Contradiction to the Scriptures, for ſuch as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed the word of God which endureth for ever, and were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by it, they had purified their ſoules through their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Truth, through the Spirit, which thou denyes, and ſo denyes their doctrine, who ſaid, Seeing yee have purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your ſoules, (have purifyed in the preſent Tenſe) in obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Truth, through the Spirit; See that yee Love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a pure heart, fervently; but thou art againſt a pure heart alſo, and ſo againſt the Scripture, 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.22.</p>
               <p>And where thou ſayes, one in Anſwer to M: <hi>Eaton, P.</hi> 14. ſaith; Did ever <hi>Paul</hi> deny perfection: Thou in Reply ſaith, what thinkes hee or others of that, <hi>Phil:</hi> 3.12. I Anſwer, hee is ſo far from denying it, that he preſſed hard after it, and ſaid to ſuch as had attained to it, preſſe others on after it, and they did; <hi>Heb:</hi> 6.1. and ſuch obtained as ſo preſſed after it; <hi>Heb:</hi> 12.22, 23. And <hi>Paul</hi> obtained it, and preached wiſdome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them that were perfect, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2.6, 7. and ſaid, <hi>Finally my Brethren, Farewell, and be perfect,</hi> but thou denyes it, and ſo contradicts the Scripture, and croſſeth the Apoſtles doctrine, therefore thou and ſuch are to be holden accurſed, <hi>Gal:</hi> 1.8.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayes, The queſtion asked of one <hi>G: Fox</hi> was, Have yee no ſin? and his Anſwer was no; I Anſwer, If it were, it was not contrary to ſuch as were in the eternall Life, and did abide in Chriſt; but hee is in the Life of Truth, and abides in Chriſt, and therefore his Anſwer did not contradict the Scripture in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114685:12"/>the 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 3.6. but agree therewith; and for that of the 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 4.16.17. it witneſſeth the ſame, though thou would wreſt it, yet thy twiſtings is not ſufficient grounds, to overthrow the truth, for it will ſtand a witneſſe againſt all Gaineſayers like thee, when thou art wearied with making oppoſition againſt it; to manifeſt thy folly as thou haſt done.</p>
               <p>And thou ſayes in Anſwer to <hi>Samuel Eaton; Pag:</hi> 19. They deny Saints to be alwayes in the warfare; if they doe, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny not the Scripture, but agrees with it; for ſuch as have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come are more then Conquerers, and thou brings that of <hi>Paul</hi> in the warfare, to contradict it, ſaying, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23.) <hi>I ſee a Law in my members warring</hi> &amp;c. but thou brings not his after Experience, where hee ſayes, the Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt, hath made mee free; <hi>Rom:</hi> 8. And where hee, with the reſt in that union with him ſaith, they are more than Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers through him that Loved them, <hi>ver:</hi> 37 and ſuch as are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally minded, as thou art, are in death, but ſuch as are ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally minded are in life and peace; and greater is hee that is in them then hee that is in the world 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 4.4. and ſuch as have overcome the wicked one knowes the father, and are ſtrong, becauſe they have overcome, and are in union with him that giveth them victory; and the word of God abideth in them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that have ſo overcome; 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 2.13 14. which thou art igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of and knoweſt not that pleads for ſin and ſo for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill; therefore his ſervant thou art expect his reward, for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his worke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Repentance.</head>
               <p>They Queſtion that Implyeth a deniall of Repentance in ſuch as make a trade of ſinne; take heed and looke to thy ſelfe, that art ſo hardened in thy ſins and pleads ſo ſtrongly for them, leaſt thou be given over to hardneſſe of heart and Repentance be hid from thee as from <hi>Eſau</hi> it was, for wee know that the goodneſſe of God leadeth to repentance and the Scripture wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth the ſame with us, therefore wee contradict it not, but agree therewith and witneſſe the gift from the Goodneſſe, <hi>Rom:</hi> 2.4. But take heed that thou harden not thine heart,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114685:12"/>and treaſure up unto thy ſelfe wrath againſt the day of wrath, and revelation of the righteous Judgement of God, <hi>ver:</hi> 5. And where thou ſayes, wee diſclaime a Godly ſorrow, which thou calls remorſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there thou haſt uttered another lye, but thou art accuſtomed to it, and it is hard for thee to leave it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Reading, Singings and Prayer, Baptiſme and the Lords Suffer <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Thou would raiſe a ſlander, and caſt it upon us from ſome words which thou haſt wreſted in the Booke called the <hi>Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of the Lord;</hi> by <hi>C: Athinſon; Pag:</hi> 22. as if wee ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the way and the meanes that God uſeth to reveale himſelfe to his people by, and through, but that is but further to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt thy lying and deceitful Spirit of errour and deceit for Chriſt is the Light, to lead out of errour, and deceit ſuch as follow him into the Light of Life <hi>Joh:</hi> 8.2. And he is the way to the Father and that wee owne, and none can come to the Father without him and hee reveales his ſecrets by his Spirit, even the deepe things of God 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2.10 and no man knowes the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but the ſonne, and he to whoſoever the ſonne will reveale him; And this doth not contradict the Scriptures but are wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed by them, <hi>Math:</hi> 11.27. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.22. But the Scriptures are not Chriſt, then they are not the Spirit that reveales the deepe things of God; But God hath ſent the Spirit of his ſonne into our hearts, whereby we cry, Abba father, <hi>Gal:</hi> 4.6. and by his Spirit hee tcacheth us to profit, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12.7. and to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 5.20. and teacheth us how to read with an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and how to pray as wee ought, <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.26. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 14.15. and that doth not contradict the 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 3.15, nor <hi>Rom:</hi> 10.17. nor <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. nor <hi>James</hi> 1 6. for wee know that faith is Given by the miniſtry of Chriſt in the Spirit, and that God giveth us his holy Spirit, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3:24. and the wiſdome which is pure, peaceable, Gentle, and eaſie to be entreated, <hi>James,</hi> 3.17. and the fruite of righteouſneſſe is ſowne in peace, of them that make peace, <hi>James</hi> 3.18. for which wee praiſe God, and owne hearing, reading and prayer, and the teachings of God, according to his promiſes; Therefore thy ſlaunder and accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114685:13"/>harmeth us not; But your braine Imaginations wee deny, and ſprinkling Infants with water, which thou calls Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall water; but canſt thou prove it; yet the Baptiſme by one Spirit we owne (1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12.12, 13.) into one body, where there is one faith, one Lord, one Baptiſme, <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 4.4, 5. and ſuch as are baptized into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt; and that wee wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as doth the Scripture, which is not Contradiction, <hi>Gal:</hi> 3.27. But ſprinkling Infants is an Invention, and none of Chriſts Inſtitution; But thou perverts the Scripture, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38, 39. ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Be baptized every one of you; you and your Children;</hi> Here thou art a lyar, It doth not Command Children to be baptized with water, neither did they ever ſo baptize them that thou canſt prove, by one plaine Scripture, and where thou ſayes that one of them ſayes, The Lords Supper is a carnall Invention; I charge thee in that to be a groſſe lyar, I ſaid that your Imagination was a carnall Invention, but the Lords Supper I owne, and witneſſe that he is come in to ſupp with mee, <hi>Rev:</hi> 3.20. And the bread which we breake, it is the communion of the body of Chriſt, and the Cup which we drinke, it is the communion of the blood of Chriſt; and as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid ſo ſay I; Let thoſe that are ſpirituall Judge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what is ſaid; but thou canſt not prove that <hi>Paul</hi> broke outward bread and drunke outward wine, with the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> nor the manner how; and therefore it is thy reaſon that is ſo weake; that ſaith <hi>The bread which you breake, although it be bread in the nature and ſubſtance, yet it is Spirit in the Inſtitution,</hi> &amp;c. What blaſphemy is this, to ſay that the Spirit is in the bread, which is naturall in the ſubſtance, here is a Papiſticall tricke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and thy reaſon is very weak to carry thee out to utter thy ſhallowneſſe and emptineſſe, of the body and blood of Chriſt; that would make that bread which is naturall in the ſubſtance, as thou ſayes, the Spirit and Life of Chriſt and ſo ſubſtantiall in the Inſtitution by yon deceivers; oh, <hi>Horrible deluſion!</hi> The Kingdome of God conſiſts not in meate and drinke, but righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, peace &amp; Joy in the holy Ghoſt; and in that kingdome wheat bread, and red wine is not ſoules food; but the pretious blood of Chriſt, &amp; ſuch as eate him they live on hum and dwells in him, he is my meate and drinke and food for my ſoule to feed on, and for ſuch as are in him <hi>John</hi> 6. <hi>Who is the bread of Life.</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:114685:13"/>And where thou ſayeſt wee are againſt publique prayer theſe thon ſayes are their very expreſſe words in Anſwer to <hi>Samuell Eaton, P:</hi> 26. contrary to the order 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 14 14. Here thou haſt manifeſted thy deceitfull ſpirit, and wronged the words in that Booke by turning them into a wrong ſenſe, by thy filthy minde, to manifeſt thy miſcheife againſt the Truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in thy deceitfull heart; for the words in that page thou haſt cited is that wee are againſt a publique prayer which is in the ſtate of the Phariſee, which Chriſt forbids, and that doth not contradict Scripture, nor the counſell of Chriſt, but agree therewith, <hi>Math:</hi> 6.5. but the praying with the Spirit we owne, and thoſe are the following words in that booke, &amp; agrees with the ſaying of Chriſt in <hi>Math:</hi> 6.6. and with the order of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in the 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 14. which is to pray with the ſpirit and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, <hi>ver:</hi> 15. Therefore thy lyes and ſlanders harmes us not; And thou ſayes, wee are againſt all <hi>Davids</hi> prayers, and propheſies, and ſinging contrary to Scripture; and cites the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>Sam: Eaton, P:</hi> 26. Let that Book witneſſe for the truth, againſt thy deceit; ſinging of Pſalmes and hymns and ſpirituall ſongs we are not againſt but owne; and <hi>Davids</hi> prayers &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies; But your Poetry we deny, and teaching people to ſing lyes in hypocriſie; ſaying, they are not puft in minde, when they are puft in minde, and ſaying, they have no ſcornfull eye, when they have, and much more of that nature, Be aſhamed lyar, and give over lying.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Elders, Miniſters Maintenance, Immediate calling, and Immediate teaching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Ordaining of Elders thou ſayes was not by man; Quoting the <hi>Diſcovery of the man of ſinne,</hi> by <hi>James Nayler, Pag:</hi> 38. Let the wiſe-hearted read that booke, and it will witneſſe, &amp; cleare him, and the truth declared in it, but this I ſay, The holy Ghoſt made Overſeers, and ſo Elders in the Church, and that doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the Scripture, but agree therewith, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. and the holy Ghoſt is not ſuch men as you are; and he ſaid, <hi>Seperate mee Barnabas &amp; Saul for the worke whereunto I have appoynted them, and they were ſent out by the holy Ghoſt,</hi> Act. 13. And he was not taught the Goſpel which he preached, of man, but of God, <hi>Gal:</hi> 1. and ſo taught immediately, and went, after Chriſt was revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114685:14"/>in him immediately, to preach the Goſpel; And thou ſayes, They ſay that God ſends forth Immediately contrary to <hi>Gal:</hi> 1. and ſaith, there <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of a ſending of man, <hi>&amp;c</hi> but that Chapter may be a ſufficient witneſſe againſt thee, &amp; prove thee to be a lyar of them, and of that booke of the warning to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbarrow</hi> by <hi>Edw: Burr:</hi> from which thou ſayes they pretend to an Infallible Judgement, &amp; to a calling, not by man but Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate, as the Prophets and Apoſtles had; whom God ſends, ſay they, he ſends Immediately, and thou ſayes that is contrary to <hi>Gal:</hi> 1. here let the Scripture be a witneſſe againſt thee, that he that was Immediately called &amp; ſent, doth there witneſſe the ſame, and as for pretences, we doe not pretend to be Immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called and ſent, but we witneſſe that we are, and ſo witneſſe with him that thou accuſeſt; and all thy Mediate calls &amp; ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings will not prove thee to be as <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; <hi>Timothy</hi> was, that had the gift within him, and the teſtimony by the holy Ghoſt, as they had, And for <hi>Rich: Farneworth,</hi> in that Booke called, <hi>Light riſen out of darkneſſe, P:</hi> 16. ſaying, The Apoſtle had a free ſpirit, and was chargeable to no man, but preached freely, he witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the ſame, and ſaid alſo that he Coveted no mans ſilver nor gold, nor apparell, but preached the Goſpel freely, &amp; his hands miniſtred to his neceſſities, That is truth, and will ſtand as a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt all proud, Covetous, ſelfe-ſeeking hireling Prieſts in <hi>Scotland</hi> &amp; elſewhere; and at the Truth which witneſſes againſt your deceit thou art offended: And where thou ſayes wee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be Immediately taught: wee doe not pretend ſo to be, as I ſaid before, but we witneſſe that we are ſo taught, &amp; according to the promiſe of the Lord; And thou that art not taught of him, ſhews that thou ſpeakes a viſion of thy owne heart &amp; not from the Mouth of the Lord; and for the true Prophets ſtudying the word, that is thy Imagination, and contrary to Scripture, for no prophecy of the Scripture came in old time by the will of man, (then not ſtudied) but holy men of God ſpoke as they were mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the holy Ghoſt, and the Scripture is of no private Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation; but thou that denies immediate teachings and ſaith the ſpirit is in the letter &amp; given by it; thou may well accuſe us falſely that ſo lyes againſt God, &amp; his Spirit, to manifeſt to all the children of Light that thou art ignorant of him and never was called nor ſent by him; but ran, as the falſe Prophets did, and ſo doth not profit the people at all, <hi>Jere:</hi> 23 <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:114685:14"/>
               <head>Concerning Queſtions.</head>
               <p>And as for Queſtions; The Novices ſhall ſtand for your ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and deceivers, who are puft up in Pride and Conceits; And where thou ſayes, They deny, or ſay Queſtions are of the Devill; ſuch Queſtions as are of the Devill we deny; But we owne Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions in their place, and therefore thou haſt caſt that out as a ſlaunder, but it is turned backe upon thee againe, receive it into thy old bottle from whence it came.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To that of thine concerning Civill honour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Civillity and honour wee owne, and knows to whom honour is due, &amp; to whom it is not; for if I honour a proud man for his pride, I diſhonour God in ſo doing for pride is one of the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations and if I honour a covetous man and an oppreſſor for his covetouſneſſe and oppreſſion I ſhould offend God in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or if I honour the Serpent and his ſeed; But all men that are joyned to the Lord, and walke in union with him, and his ſeed, I honour &amp; love, and this I ſpeake in ſincerity; and yet beſides all this, I can love my enemies: But to follow fooliſh idle fancies, to worſhip men with cap and knee, and flatteries, as the Serpents feed doe, and which thou pleads for, we doe that deny, &amp; againſt it teſtifie, &amp; how can yee beleive that ſeeks honour one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; ſeeks not the honour that cometh of God onely, <hi>Joh:</hi> 5.44. and what the Scriptures doe allow, we doe know, without thy ranking together, but where doth the Scripture ſay, put off your hatts, and flatter with your tongues, as proud fleſh, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, and ſuch as thou doſt; or where doth it ſay, reſpect the rich, and diſreſpect the poore: Are you not partiall, and of them that have mens perſons in admiration, becauſe of advantage, &amp; have reſpect to perſons for ſelfe-ends, and ſo are Infidells and out of the faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt which is not with ſuch reſpect of perſons, for ſelfe-ends, and carnall conſiderations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Oaths.</head>
               <p>And where thou ſayes, They take up the words of Chriſt, <hi>Math:</hi> 5.34. <hi>Sweare not at all;</hi> as they doe other Scriptures, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his meaning, as if they did abſolutely exhibit all oaths, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Magiſtrate whereas (thou ſayes) he forbids oaths onely by creatures, heaven and earth a mans head, &amp;c The ſame mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114685:15"/>thou ſayes hath <hi>James;</hi> Thou ſayes, Chriſt doth not forbid all oaths (but by creatures onely, here thou art a lyar of Chriſt, and his words beares teſtimony againſt thee for he doth not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid ſwearing by creatures onely, but he forbids ſwearing by all things els, whatſoever, for he ſaith, <hi>Sweare not at all, neither by heaven, for it is Gods Throne, nor by earth, for it is his footſtoole;</hi> (and he that ſweares not by heaven muſt not ſweare by what is contained in it, &amp; he that ſweares not by earth, muſt not ſweare by what is contained in it) but Chriſt forbids ſwearing by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, and ſo by things contained in them; and likewiſe the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſayes <hi>Sweare not at all,</hi> and if a man muſt not ſweare at all, then he muſt not ſweare by a booke or any other thing; And though thou plead againſt the doctrine of Chriſt; and ſaith, he doth not forbid all oaths, but by creatures onely, yet to confute thy ſelfe and manifeſt thy contradictions thou ſayes he forbids not ſwearing by creatures onely but all oaths, and here out of confuſion thou haſt confeſt to the Truth after thou hadſt contradicted it; And if thou had not made ſwearing null and voyd by thy words, in confeſſing that all oaths are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, The very expreſſe words of Scripture would have been a witneſſe clearely in the ſecond place againſt thee, <hi>James</hi> 5.12. And as for this ſaying, we take the words of Chriſt contrary to his meaning; therein thou haſt alſo in that cleared us, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted thy ſelfe; for we take his words according to his mind, and ſo denies oaths, &amp; abides in his doctrine; But the Lord hath ſuffered thee to lay open thy folly, that by thy words thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be judged, &amp; knowne to be in confuſion, &amp; ſelfe contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo Babyloniſh; Take heed of uttering thy folly as thou haſt done.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Selfe Contradictions.</head>
               <p>And where thou ſayes, they deny the Letter of the Scriptures to be Scripture, (that is one of thy lyes) and yet thou ſayes they ſtick to the Letter of the Scripture, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.8, 10. which ſaith, <hi>Be not called Maſters;</hi> here thou haſt cleared them, and contradicted thy ſelfe againe; but thou art offended that they witneſſe againſt thy deceit, and cuts of thy Maſterſhip, by thy own rule, though thou wouldſt cover it over, yet thy covers are ſeen and thou art left bare: And thou ſayes they ſay, he that believeth hath the witneſſe in himſelfe, and if they ſay ſo, the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114685:15"/>Scripture ſaith the ſame, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10. herein they do not deny nor croſſe the Scriptures: Acknowledge thy lies, error and confuſion, and upon them own thy condemnation; for after thou haſt ſaid that they ſhould ſay, They deny the Letter of the Scripture to be Scripture, to confute thy ſelfe and clear them in p. 21 thou ſayes that they ſay, the Scriptures they own, to be true in themſelves, as they were given forth by the ſpirit of truth, which ruled in them that gave them forth, and for proof ſets down, Light riſen out of darkneſſe by <hi>Richard Farneworth</hi> p. 13. here both thy own witneſſe and that Book of <hi>Richard Farneworths</hi> doth witneſſe aganſt thee: And thus thou haſt cleared them from the ſlander that thou ſought to caſt upon them, and art under the guilt, and the pit which for others thou diggedſt, thou are faln in thy ſelfe, and catcht in thy own ſnare and craftineſſe, take notice of that, &amp; ſee how thou haſt contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted thy ſelfe: And where thou ſayes one of them ſaith, you are ignorant of the life of the Scriptures that are ignorant of the Letter, herein thou haſt manifeſted the ſame, therefore take thou the ſhame; for the life from whence the Scriptures pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded is not the Letter, yet the Letter doth declare of it; and ſuch as thou art, that had the Letter but were ignorant of the Life, Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> in them you think you have eternall life, <hi>they teſtifie of me,</hi> but ſaith he, <hi>Ye will not come to me that ye might have life,</hi> John 5. 39, 40. And againe ſaith he, <hi>I am the Way the Truth and the Life,</hi> Joh. 14.6. And he that hath the Son hath Life, but the Son is not the Letter nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the Letter the Son, yet the Letter declares of him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the new Birth, and the word in the heart.</head>
               <p>He that believeth, thay ſay, is born of God: I anſwer, ſo ſaith the Scripture, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. and that the word of Faith is nigh in the heart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is witneſſed <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8. and he that believes and is born of God knowes the ſeed of God within him, as ſaith the Scripture. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.9. but he is not born of the Letter as thou wouldſt have him, yet he is begotten by the immortall word, which endureth for ever, which the Letter declares of and that doth not contradict the Scripture: Therefore where thou twines about to raiſe a lye of them, ſaying they ſay and unſay, that is thy own, as before is proved; for thou art he that ſayes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114685:16"/>and unſayes; and where thou ſayes take the meaning of their words; that haſt not the ſame minde, knows not the meaning, but wreſts them, as thou perverts the Scriptures, and ſo raiſeth lyes by thy imaginations; to manifeſt alſo thy contradictions; for thou ſayes, they ſay and ſay truly, (then they lye not) nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do they ſay and unſay; and thou ſayes they ſay truly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Scripture ſaith ſo, then they agree with the Scripture, being of God and ſpeaking truly, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.4, 5, 6. and they that are of God hear his word, then they croſſe not the Scripture, neither do they ſay and unſay if they ſay truly (and as thou alſo ſay,) But they ſay truly, therefore they do not ſay and unſay, and ſo thou art taken with the lye againe, and clears them thy ſelf; and where thou ſayes they deny that in <hi>John</hi> 1.9. to be a naturall Light, If we do, we have warrant for it, for it is the Light ſupernaturall, <hi>John</hi> 8.12. and if one of them did ſay he lived in a naturall condition before his converſion, is that ſuch a ſtrange thing, ſuch as were witneſſes for God, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and others had been naturall before they were ſpirituall, and when it pleaſed God to reveal his Son in them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. he alſo commanded the Light to ſhine out of darkneſſe, to give them the knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Jeſus, and they had the heavenly treaſure manifeſted in earthen veſſels, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6, 7. and if it had not been there in a myſtery, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 27. how could it in them have been ſo after manifeſted (in them,) but that thou art mindfull to cavill on purpoſe againſt the work of God, to ſhew forth the envy of thy heart againſt the breakings forth of Light, whereby your deeds of darkneſſe are diſcoverd, and againſt teſtified: And where thou ſayes they magnifie the Light and the Law written in the heart, to judge and condemn ſin; then thou ſayes, the day of Judgment is come: I anſwer, Where Judgement is brought forth into victory, ſin is condemned in the fleſh, and there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, who walk not after the fleſh but after the ſpirit, and ſuch have boldneſſe in the day of Judgement; for as ſome mens deeds goes before hand to Judgement others they come after, and therefore a day of Judgement is to come, and that thou and the wicked will know to be a day of torment (though the righteous may rejoyce in it:) Againe thou ſayes, They affirme that every man in his firſt eſtate may fee himſe;fe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114685:16"/>to be naturall, but not able to judge of the things of God, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting particulers concerning the Law by <hi>John Cam,</hi> let that book be a witneſſe to the truth, againſt thy ignorance and ſottiſhnes that ſets thy corruptions and pleads for them; the light which doth diſcover the naturall corruptions, is not not naturall, as thou ſayes, but it is ſpirituall, and ſuch as love it bring their deeds to be tryed by it, and with it the deceits is Judged, and ſuch as dwell in the Light that Judges in the particuler, where it rules them, and they are united to it, may with it Judge and diſcerne betwixt truth and errour; but ſuch as with the Light have the deeds of darkneſſe diſcovered, and hates the Light, the Light is their condemnation, as it is thine, and they that are in union with corruptions, as thou art, they are not able to Judge of the things of God, but erre in judgement that judgeth with evill thoughts, as thou doſt, and haſt done, therefore judgements is to thy head and crown of deceit, pride and vaine glory: thou ſayes one of them ſayes, the leaſt degree of Light manifeſted in the creature is perfect in its meaſure and in its ſelf, few words, by <hi>James Nayler,</hi> let that book alſo witneſſe againſt thy ſubtilty, which is a witneſſe againſt thy generation, and thou goes on &amp; ſayes, if the Light be perfect both in its meaſure and in its ſelfe, then it is perfect every way; thou haſt here confeſſed, that if the Light be perfect in its meaſure and in its ſelfe, then it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect every way; but thy imaginations cannot finde out the higheſt degree, that are not ſubject to the loweſt, but acts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to it, and ſo to be condemned by it; for it is perfect, both in reſpect of its truth, and ſincerity, power and authority, and condemns the haters and reſiſters of it; but guides and leads ſuch as love and obey it, into the life and power, that they are able to comprehend with all Saints what is the height and depth and length and bredth of the love of God, and they are in uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the higheſt and loweſt in their meaſures and degrees, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the working of the divine power of God, who worketh according to the good pleaſure of his will, and he that hath his ſins covered is bleſſed; but thy meaning is denied, and no other Chriſt doe we owne, but Chriſt which is the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever, who doth perfect them that he ſanctifies; and the righteouſneſs of Chriſt is our righteouſneſſe, who are ſaved from our ſins by him, and we witneſs him to be the alone Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114685:17"/>of all that obey him; and perfectly able to ſave to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt all thoſe that come unto God by him; But all thy ſcra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped up ſtuffe, &amp; thy twiſtings and windings we deny; who ſaith, the ſpirit is in the letter, and the ſpirit is given by the letter; and ſaith, The true Light, to wit, Chriſt, that lighteth every man that cometh into the world with his light; (which thou ſayes is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and common, and ſaith, that no man could know that he hath the witneſſe in himſelfe, but by the Scriptures, and ſo thou would have the Spirit to be bought &amp; ſold, if it were in the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; to be given by it; And thou would have a letter-Saviour, if the letter could give the ſpirit &amp; eternall life; And thou would have a letter-fulneſſe, and no witneſſe of God without the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and if the letter ſhould be loſt, the fulneſſe and the witneſſe would be loſt, and ſo have God to be without witneſſes, and his people without ſupply and ſtrength, according to thy account; for thou ſayes, that none could know that he that beleiveth hath the witneſſe in himſelfe, but by the Scriptures; &amp; here thou ſets the Scripture in the roome of God, and of Chriſt, &amp; gives all the preheminence to the letter of the Scripture, and not to Chriſt, and that is contrary to the Scriptures; for he (to wit, Chriſt) is before all things, and by him all things conſiſt, and he is the head of the body the Church, who is the beginning and firſt borne from the dead, that in all things hee might have the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, for in him the fulneſſe dwells, then not in the Letter, yet the Letter declares of it; <hi>Coloſ:</hi> 1.17, 18, 19.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Concerning Quaking &amp; trembling, and Growth in Grace,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayes they profeſſe Quaking and trembling after the manner of <hi>Moſes, Habbakuck, David, Paul,</hi> &amp; other, and yet are ſome of them the moſt daring creatures that ever (thou ſayes) thou heard ſpeake, or obſerved to put pen to paper, &amp; will ſtand in an evill cauſe before Magiſtraces, without Quaking or feare, ſetting downe <hi>Rich: Farnworth, Reply</hi> 2.5. I Anſwer, The ſame power that made <hi>Moſes, Habbacuck, David, Paul,</hi> and the reſt to Quake, ſhake and tremble, the ſame power wee witneſſe, and working out our ſalvation with feare and trembling, God work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in us, to will, and to doe alſo, after his owne good pleaſure, and this is no contradiction to Scriptures, but thou that ſpeakes againſt the power of God, that worketh effectually in his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as it did in them, that witneſſed Quaking &amp; trembling; &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114685:17"/>trembling and Quaking, that proceeds from the power of God witneſſed of in Scripture, thou therein contradicts the Scripture; and for that ſaying, or falacy of thine, where thou haſt ſhot out thy ſting in thy tayle ſaying, we will ſtand in an Evill cauſe before Magiſtrates without Quaking or feare; herein thou art taught thy gradations methodically in old Antichriſts ſchoole to lye, ſlander, accuſe falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and jeere, and cannot prove what thou haſt ſaid; ſtop thy mouth deceiver, and take in thy ſlander againe; and as for being bold to witneſſe the Truth, againſt deceit, that doth ſore offend thee, and ſuch Scotch deceivers, &amp; all deceivers, ſuch as thou art; but the Lord maketh the righteous as bold as Lyons; that he teacheth to profit, and to grow from grace to grace, to ſet forth his praiſe, glory be to him for ever; and where thou ſayes they ſay they witnes the Saints Growth &amp; the time of preſſing on to perfection, art thou offended at that; They that witneſſe the ſame doe not therein croſſe nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the Scripture; And where thou ſayes they owne the fruits of the Spirit, art thou offended alſo at that, and doth the old Serpent teach thee to lye againſt the Spirit with the fruits of it &amp; them that are guided by it <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.14. &amp; <hi>Gal:</hi> 5 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 3. and falſely accuſe them ſaying they walke in the moſt manifeſt fruits of the fleſh; in that all that feares God, &amp; knows their godly converſation may witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee; &amp; herein thou haſt manifeſted thy ſpirit of errour &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit &amp; to be one that regards not what thou ſayes, (&amp; as for ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing at Scottiſh Prieſts or others that we deny but your raiſing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives tryalls, points, reaſons, and uſes, out of other mens words, and ſpeaking a divination of your owne braine, for your owne ends, by plaine Scripture you cannot it juſtifie; therefore againſt you &amp; ſuch deceivers as profeſſe Scriptures to be your rule, and act contrary to them, we declare &amp; againſt you teſtifie and as for your formes of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit we deny but a forme of ſound words the Scripture doth juſtifie, being ſpoken by the Spirit of truth, which we owne: and now the time is come that deceivers &amp; ſuch as you are cannot endure ſound doctrine, but utters your folly, to make your ſelves manifeſt; &amp; what generation you are of, even of him, whoſe comming is after the working of Satan, with all deceiveable of unrighteouſneſſe in them that periſh, 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 2. 2 <hi>Pet:</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Concerning Ordinances, Inſtructing of Children, and the Reſurrection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Praying in familyes (thou ſayes) they ſay they own, with reading and inſtructing of Children and bringing them up in the feare of the Lord, and teaching according to the Apoſtles doctrine proved by a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114685:18"/>ſhort Anſwer to 7 Prieſts <hi>P:</hi> 19. which thou haſt cited, and art thou offended at this; ſet thy conceivings, that ariſeth out of thy darke minde aſide, and thy vaine Imaginations and cloſe to the Truth, and ſtand not up to oppoſe it, wilfully, leaſt thou be found one of thoſe that ſins wilfully after grace received, to whom there is no more ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, for ſin but a fearful looking for of Judgement &amp; fiery Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Lord which ſhall devour the Adverſaries; and where thou ſayes they pretend to owne all that is Gods, we doe owne that which is Gods free love &amp; mercy to us and all that is Gods, as Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme the Lords Supper<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Church-fellowſhip, Sabboth: The fleſh of Chriſt &amp; the reſurrection and all that we owne, and what thou haſt cited out of the book of <hi>James Naylers,</hi> called <hi>Spirituall wickedneſſe in heavenly places,</hi> or an anſwer to a book entituled, <hi>Freedome of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Worſhip, or the Jubile of Ordinances ſet forth;</hi> Let the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted read that book to further witneſſe for the Truth, on our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, &amp; to be a witneſſe againſt their deceit; &amp; ſuch as would falſely ſlander and reproach us and the Truth; and where thou ſayes, there muſt be no Lawes concerning Religion; yet ſays, they admoniſh Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers to ſee that their Lawes be according to that in the Conſcience; of every man; &amp; then thou ſays after thou haſt wreſted their words, by this it ſeemes there is no Religion in the Conſcience, or els why ſhould there not be Lawes according to religion aſwel as according to the Conſcience; Thou deceitfull Spirit, how haſt thou wreſted the words ſet downe about the Law of God, which anſwers his Juſtice, &amp; the Light in the Conſcience, which anſwers the law of God which is perfect, according to that in the conſcience; Let the wiſe-hearted read that Booke, which thou haſt wreſted, called, <hi>The Glory of the Lord, ariſing ſhaking terribly the earth &amp; overturning all, untill righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe be ſet up;</hi> being an Encounter with the Miniſters of the world, touching their Maintenance, wherein they are beaten with their owne Weapons; confuted by their owne Scriptures, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, and that will ſufficiently witneſſe againſt thy lyes; &amp; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt to the Law of God, which is for Eſtabliſhing Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and ſeeing thy lyes are ſo made manifeſt, I ſhall leave this to the ſimple-hearted that they may take notice of thy deceits, herein made manifeſt, beſides much filthineſſe in thy booke of ſlanders<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where thou deceifully haſt wreſted our words, by thy ſorcery and witcheraft, but Truth is cleared, and thou art enſnared and proved to be the contradicter of Scriptures, and not thoſe whom thou ſcornfully calls <hi>Quakers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:114685:18"/>
               <head>This is a Teſtimony againſt that Pamphlet (nameleſſe Author) called, The ſerious reveiw of ſome Principles of the <hi>Quakers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN a paper called, <hi>A ſerious review of ſome Principles of the</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers; one that ſaith, He hath ceaſed from man, and is dead to Sects; and ſaith, There is many in this Age who do own in their judgement many parts of Truth, or ſeverall ſound Principles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as it were by peecemeal, who notwithftanding many more things, if not in the moſt, do erre: And as for error &amp; deceit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der refined ſubtilty, that is the condition of die man that ſaith, He is dead to all Sects, but he is yet alive in the opinions, and ſtands on the ground of fancies, and fil'd with conceits, and catching at truths in the notion, but errs not knowing the ſeed of God, nor the Key of the true Knowledge, nor the Spirit that ſtands before the Throne, the flaming Sword, nor the Cherub, but is ſhut out of the ground of Truth, grinding and making meal, or proviſion for the Luſt, feeding with the Serpent upon duſt; and yet with his high aiery notions, and coloured expreſſions, thinks to hide himſelf, but is bare to the ſingle eyed: He ſaith, he ſhall lay down ſeveral prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and as he propounds them he ſhall refute them, yet ſhall ſpeak of none of them but ſuch as be moſt known, that they may not have it to ſay that he wreſts their words and do bely them; but in the firſt place, thou wreſts and belies the words of <hi>J: Nayler,</hi> and <hi>G: Fox,</hi> let the wiſe hearted read <hi>Sauls</hi> errand and the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> page in the Anſwer to the perfect Phariſee, and the words are not as thou haſt ſet them down, therefore thou art a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verter of them and a lyar, and inſtead of defending the Truth thou art labouring to uphold the Deceit, but thoſe two Books ſhall wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for the Truth, againſt thy fancy and whimſie amongſt all thy ſcraped up ſtuffe; this is the weight or matter that thou ſtumbles at, as if there ſhould be ſomething in man that is not creared; what is the ſeed of God that keeps ſuch as are born of God that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not commit ſin, &amp; that which is born after the will of God, in whom that ſeed abides, which is as the winde that bloweth, and no man knows by his will the manner of the work brought forth by it but he that is not of the world, and what is that unction that abideth in ſuch, which teacheth them all things, &amp; is truth and no lye; Is that holy unction created, &amp; is not that in the regenerate? And the holy Ghoſt is that created, and is not that in ſuch, and abides in them, &amp; that myſterie of Faith which is held in a pure conſcience, what is that, is it not in man? and what is that which bruiſes the Serpents
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114685:19"/>head, and the myſtery of godlines in man? And ſuch as are ſo joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to that ſeed, &amp; in union with that one ſpirit, thou and the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot are ignorant of them and that myſterie, &amp; therefore thou mayſt ſtop thy mouth, for thou haſt manifeded thy ignorance, and knows not our Principles, they are not for thee to take up to carry about in thy foul reaſon, &amp; dirty mire imagination, words that proceeds from the Principle thou imagins of, but knows neither the Principle nor the Power in which we ſtand, that knows not that there is ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in man that is eternall; &amp; therefore thou knows not the ſeed of God, the holy Ghoſt, the unction, the life which comes down from Heaven, nor that God in Saints dwells and walks according to his Promiſe, nor that Chriſt is glorified in them; and being igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the life of God in Saints, thou muſt needs erre and lie, being out of the living truth, &amp; guided by a ſpirit of error and deceit, thou canſt do no other: &amp; as for the ſoule which thou puzzles thy minde about, thou art ignorant of, that knows not the living word of God, which devides aſunder betwixt ſoule and ſpirit, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture declareth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. and the Serpent being head in thee; he is ranging and raking up ſtuffe out of the bottomles pit to hide and cover himſelf withall, but thou art ſeen and weighed, and thou art offended at the Saints life, as the Serpents ſeed ever was, and all thy wreſtings cannot ſeperate the Father and the Son aſunder, and he that hath the Father hath the Son, and eternall life abiding it: him, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.11, 12. and abiding in the doctrine of Chriſt, he hath both the Father &amp; the Son, 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. and is changed from glory to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry into the ſame pure Image, which thou art ignorant of, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17, 18. and he that hath ſaid, the Father and the Son are one, &amp; I and my Father are one, doth not contradict Scripture, as thou doſt, and alſo as <hi>J: Stalham</hi> doth, who himſelf pleads for bread &amp; wine, as an Ordinance, to laſt till Chriſt come perſonally upon earth, and to be a ſubſtantiall Chriſt in that bread at inſtitution, and to have a ſpirit in the bread, and a ſpirit in the Letter and to be given by it, &amp; to be born of the Scripture, &amp; ſuch like ſtuffe as that, being his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurations, and without bottome from the word; and ſo you are thoſe that denye; Gods indwelling in Saints, that knows not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing eternall in them; God is not created; and he hath ſaid, <hi>I will dwell in them and walke in them,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 6 16. and the life of Chriſt is manifeſt in Saints bodies, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 4. and the Father &amp; the Son are in union together in them that are ſanctified and preſerved 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. and as Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>At that day ye ſhall know that I am
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114685:19"/>in my Father, and you in me and I in you,</hi> Joh. 14.20. &amp; ſuch may wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe him; and great is the admiration where Chriſt is glorified in Saints, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. &amp; that the ſame minde is in them that is in him, <hi>Phil:</hi> 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. and that God ſends the ſpirit of his Sonne into their hearts that they cry Abba Father, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. wonderfull is the love of God to his children, &amp; to be admired, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. which thou art a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger unto, as thou haſt made thy ſelf manifeſt: And to thy 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, that the light of Chriſt is the light of the world is witneſſed; &amp; the true light that lighteth every man that comes into the world; &amp; ſuch as follow him the true light, are led by him into the Light of Life which light is the condemnation of ſuch as hate it &amp; act contrary to it and that accuſation of thine before is written to, in anſwer to <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Stalham,</hi> thy companion in the Evill, who are both acting againſt the truth, &amp; ſo ſerving the Devill, &amp; for that Booke of <hi>James Naylor</hi> in anſwer to the perfect Phariſee It will ſtand as a witneſſe againſt you, and your generation &amp; alſo all the other bookes which you wreſted, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſhake any child of Truth; they ſtand upon you &amp; ſee you pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted harlots, to be deckt &amp; coloured with the whores atire &amp; you and your ſtuffe is fuel for the fire. And to thy 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> that ſome are come out of the fall, that we witneſſe &amp; that the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> hath redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and is redeeming what the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> loſt &amp; bleſſed are all they that waite for him but thou art oppoſing the Truth, &amp; ſcraping up Scriptures, to plead for ſin, &amp; to prove that <hi>Adam</hi> in a covenant of workes, before he fell, and contradicts thy ſelfe therein, as before is proved, &amp; makes thy ſelfe manifeſt to be in the fall, and yet under the curſe: And to thy 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> no ſin nor ſuch imperfect thing can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God nor enter into his kingdome, is true and witneſſed, which thou accuſeſt <hi>James Naylor</hi> of; and to ſhew forth thy deceit, thou ſayes, Reaſon would thinke that no perfect thing could be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God; &amp; here thy reaſon would joine the ſeed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent &amp; the ſeed of God together but cannot: 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 6.9, 10 <hi>Rev.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 8.27. for it and thou art ſhut out with the Light which thou art an enemie unto, and when thou haſt ſcraped up much ſtuffe to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, then thou cloſeſt it up with 2 or 3 Scriptures, as if God and ſin could be reconciled together which cannot be; but Chriſt being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted to take away ſin &amp; deſtroy the workes of the Devill, 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 3.3, 4, 5. &amp;c. he is the way &amp; makes way to reconcile ſuch to God, Juſtifying them from ungodlineſſe; and ſanctifying them, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 6.11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. for both he that ſanctifieth, and they that are ſanctified are all one, for which cauſe he is not aſhamed to call them brethren,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114685:20"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.11. &amp; ſo he that brings many ſons unto glory, <hi>v.</hi> 10. doth take away their ſins and ſanctifies them, and preſents them blameles and perfect before God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. without ſpot or wrinkle or any ſuch thing, <hi>v:</hi> 26, 27. and where there is ſin there is ſpot and wrinkle &amp; ſuch like things; and that concluſion of thine is a falſe one, and from the ſpirit of deceit, that would reconcile God and ſin together, but that ſoul in whom ſin hath dwelt, being ſeperated from ſin is made righteous, and the creature alſo, and being ſanctified is reconciled, which thou art ignorant of, and of the ſeed in him, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. that is born of God, and ſo ſanctified, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22, 23. <hi>And the unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall not inherit the Kingdome of god,</hi> then ſuch are not recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10, 11. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19, 20. <hi>And there ſhall in no wiſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into it any thing that defileth;</hi> but ſin defileth, therefore God and ſin are not reconciled, nor ſuch as live and act in it, and plead for it; neither whatſoever worketh abomination, or maketh a lye, (look to it ye unrighteous ones) but ſuch ſhall enter as are without ſin, and are reconciled, being written in the Lambs book of life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27. To thy ſixt, That Jeſus Chriſt is the onely Light, and no other Light beſides him to ſalvation; this is one thing that thou ſeeks to oppoſe, and accuſe <hi>J: Nayler</hi> for: Oh! that ever man ſhould be ſo blinde, and carried on wilfully, to act the Devills part, as thou art; thy ſcraped up ſtuffe I turn unde; and witneſſe againſt thy ſpirit, and I witneſſe that Chriſt is the true Light, and the way to the Father, and the alone Saviour of all that obey him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.8, 9. and perfectly able to ſave all that come unto God by him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. without any thing, contrary to him, or the invention and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vination of thy brain, or ſuch in thy nature, as further is cleared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Anſwer to thy partaker <hi>Joh: Stalham;</hi> But thou muſt needs buſie thy minde, to run over the ſame things, to ſhew forth thy fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and all that knows God they know that there is no other way, nor Light, to come to the Father by, and to ſalvation, but by Jeſus Chriſt: and if thou canſt produce another way beſides him, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Light, pretended by thee to lead to ſalvation lets know thy ſhallownes in it, who hath ſet thy ſelf to invent, and follows inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and conceits of thy braine; but I ſee by thy Eight that thou as well as <hi>John Stalham,</hi> would have a Letter Light, a Letter word, and ſo a Letter Saviour; and calls Chriſt reaſon, as he calls him na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and common; but for all the Scriptures you have ranked together, not one of them ſaith, that Chriſt the true Light is a naturall and common Light, as <hi>John Stalham</hi> ſayes, who gives the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:114685:20"/>Letter the preheminence, and not Chriſt; and ſo contradicts the Scriptures; But thou haſt manifeſted thy Rantiſme; and both of you, you are found to be enemies to the Spirit and lyars of the Scriptures alſo; And after thou haſt winded about to cover thy ſelfe in the latter end of thy eight, thou haſt left thy ſelfe bare, when all the Scriptures thou haſt gathered together, and thy rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, will not nor cannot prove the Scriptures to be eternall life; then not that word which endureth for ever; nor the word by which the worlds were made, nor the Spirit &amp; power of life, nor Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, upon which the Prophets and Apoſtles were builded; but thou ſayes (&amp; ſayes falſly) that the Scriptures which thou calls the Word, is called the foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles, ſetting downe <hi>Eph:</hi> 2.20. Now that very Scripture witneſſeth againſt thee &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes thee; for it calls Chriſt the foundation of the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and the chiefe corner ſtone in whom all the building fitly framed groweth unto an holy temple in the Lord; (not in the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) but in the Lord in whom they was builded together, for an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation of God through the Spirit, (and not through the Letter) but through the Spirit, <hi>Eph:</hi> 2.20, 21, 22. And ſay they through him (through Chriſt not the Scripture) but through Chriſt; They both had an acceſſe, not by the Letter (as thou affirmes) but by the Spirit, <hi>Eph:</hi> 2 18. How haſt thou uttered thy folly, and lyed of the Spirit, that called Chriſt the foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtle; and thou ſays, the Scriptures are, and in that thou haſt lyed of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures alſo; for the words that are left upon record witneſſes againſt thee, and both thou and <hi>John Stalham</hi> have ſhewed your ignorance of Chriſt the foundation, of the Prophets and Apoſtles, &amp; your foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is the words which witneſſe againſt you, and all lyars, &amp; thou haſt manifeſted the ſame, that the Letter is your ground, for thou ſaith it is the ground of your faith, <hi>P:</hi> 12. and ſo your faith is not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſt, which is the Saints ground; for they witneſſe Jeſus Chriſt to be the Author and finiſher of their faith, <hi>Heb:</hi> 12.2. But the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is your ground of faith, thou ſays and ſo no Scripture no faith. no faith no ſalvation; and let all the wiſe in heart ſee if thou would not here have a letter Saviour, but it is good that fooles utter their folly that others may learne to be wiſe; And where thou art offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at thou and thee, words of truth, and the Scripture Language: there thou croſſeth the Scripture &amp; contradicts them for thou canſt not ſhew one plain ſcripture in all the Bible that ſays you to one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle perſon; &amp; all thy twiſting in the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> is but to plead for deceit: and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:114685:21"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and Civill honour, wee are not to learne that of one that is out of the counſell of Chriſt, as thou art, and knowes not the eternall Word; which thou and <hi>John Stalham</hi> have ſhewed your ſelves Ignorant of, and to be without the Spirit of Chriſt, to guide you, and ſuch are not his; And as for things that ſtands in the Counſell of Chriſt, and agrees with his Word, wee are ſubject unto, and owne true and juſt Government, and the authority: But your lyes, flattery and deceit, and ſcraped up ſtuffe wee doe deny, and againſt you, and your deceitfull Spirits dee wee declare and teſtifie: And as for that Booke, which is without a printed Name, that hath <hi>P: E:</hi> at it; this ſhall be as a witneſſe againſt it, with the following words, alſo, as a concluſion againſt your deluſion; There is a Paper from the ſame ſpirit of errour and deceit, comed out of <hi>Scotland</hi> without a name, the Author being either convicted in his Conſcience that hee hath belyed the Truth, or els ſome ſhame to owne that for truth which hee hath publiſhed, or ſome ſuch like thing; but though his name be hid, his heart is uncovered to the ſingle eyed; (and if <hi>Peter En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> be his name) his ſpirit is weighed and tryed, with the light that mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſts his ſubtilty, flattery, deceit, ſecret ennity, and ſerpentine pollicy; and hee and thou <hi>John Stalham</hi> are both in one myſtery of Iniquity, and becauſe hee hath in effect or ſubſtance the ſame things ſcraped up that thou haſt; This which I have written ſhall be as a witneſſe againſt you both, and the Light in your Conſciences, as the booke of Concience is opened will remember you in the bed of torment, and be a ſwift witneſſe againſt you, and be your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demenation, that hare it, and ſet your ſelves to worke wickedneſſe, and that Light which convinceth you of the evill of your wayes, will let you ſee your ſelves, as Conſcience booke is opened, to be the vileſt, and of the ſame ſpirit of wickedneſſe (though under a refined ſubtilty) that the vileſt of men are, and that Light which yon now hate and ſcorne will remember you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of what (againſt it and the Lord) you have acted and done, and the thoughts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of your hearts, will be ſeene and diſcovered by it; and you, and all that hate it, will by Chriſt the Light of the World be judged, and rewarded, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the deeds done in your bodyes, and in the day of the Lords fierce wrath you will know the Judge of hearts, and that you cannot hide your ſelves from him, all your covers will be too narrow, in the day of wrath, when you are caſt into a bed of Torment; remembered you will be, now you are warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though with deceit your hearts will be filled, and with ſubtilty againſt the Truth, you be armed; It is hard for you to kicke againſt p ickes: But for the ſimple ones ſake have I written this, that they may be aware of your ſubtilty, leaſt they be deceived by you, and partake of the plagues with you.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Written by a ſervant of the Lord, knowne to the World by the name of</hi> Richard Farneworth.</signed>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Balbie</hi> in <hi>Yorkeſhire</hi>
                     <date>the 22<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Month. 55.</date>
                     <hi>England.</hi>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
